<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-cdni-triggers-extensions-02" updates='8007' ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="CDNI Control Interface / Triggers Extensions">CDNI Control Triggers Interface Extensions</title>

    <author fullname="Ori Finkelman" initials="O." surname="Finkelman">
      <organization>Qwilt</organization>


      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6, Ha'harash</street>

          <city>Hod HaSharon</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>4524079</code>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+972-72-2221647</phone>

        <email>ori.finkelman.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sanjay Mishra" initials="S." surname="Mishra">
      <organization>Verizon</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13100 Columbia Pike</street>

          <city>Silver Spring</city>

          <region>MD</region>

          <code>20904</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>sanjay.mishra@verizon.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
         This document updates RFC 8007 to include generic extensions and more
         granular content matching options, required by the Open Caching architecture.
         The Open Caching working group of the Streaming Video Alliance is focused on
         the delegation of video delivery request from commercial CDNs to a caching
         layer at the ISP. In that aspect, Open Caching is a specific use case of CDNI,
         where the commercial CDN is the upstream CDN (uCDN) and the ISP caching layer
         is the downstream CDN (dCDN). The extensions specified in this document to the
         CDNI Control Interface / Triggers are derived from requirements of Open Caching
         but are applicable to CDNI use cases in general.
      </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
         "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
         document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
         target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document defines the objects and extensions required for granular content management
         operations. For that purpose it extends CDNI Control Interface / Triggers <xref target="RFC8007"/>
         by adding new content selection options to the trigger specification and specifying a generic
         extension mechanism that enables adding future functions for controlling the trigger execution.
         This document also defines and initial set of extension objects. This document gives examples
         for the extensions specified herein, for complete examples of the trigger interface usage see
         Section 6 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>.
      </t>

      <t>The CDNI Metadata Interface is described in <xref target="RFC8006"/>.</t>
      <t>The CDNI Footprint and Capability Interface is described in <xref target="RFC8008"/>.</t>
      <t>The CDNI Control Interface / Triggers is described in <xref target="RFC8007"/>.</t>

      <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>This document reuses the terminology defined in <xref target="RFC6707"/>,
           <xref target="RFC8006"/>, <xref target="RFC8007"/>, and <xref target="RFC8008"/>.</t>

        <t>Additionally, the following terms are used throughout this document
          and are defined as follows:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>HLS - HTTP Live Streaming</t>
            <t>DASH - Dynamic Adaptive Streaming Over HTTP</t>
            <t>MSS - Microsoft Smooth Streaming</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="structure" title="Structure of this document">
        <t>
          The remainder of this document is organized as follows:
        </t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t><xref target="overview"/> gives an overview of the extensions specified in this document.</t>
            <t><xref target="cit-version-v2"/> specifies version 2 of the CDNI Control Interface / Triggers. </t>
            <t><xref target="trigger-extension-objects"/> specifies an initial set of trigger extension objects.</t>
            <t><xref target="footprint-and-capabilities"/> specifies Footprint and Capability objects for CI/T version
                and extensions.</t>
            <t><xref target="IANA"/> list the IANA considerations of this document.</t>
            <t><xref target="Security"/> describes the security considerations for the specified properties and extensions.</t>
        </list></t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="overview" title="Interfaces Extensions Overview">
      <t>
         This document defines extensions for the CDNI Control Interface / Triggers (CI/T) <xref target="RFC8007"/>
         and defines FCI objects as per the CDNI Footprint and Capabilities Interface <xref target="RFC8008"/>.
      </t>

      <section title="CDNI Control Interface / Triggers Extensions">
        <section title="CI/T Objects">
          <t>
             This document specifies version 2 of the CI/T commands and objects.
             In this context the CI/T commands and objects as were specified in
             <xref target="RFC8007"/> are considered to be version 1.
           </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="trigger-spec" title="Trigger Specification">
          <t>
             This document specifies version 2 of the Trigger Specification which is an enhancement of
             the Trigger Specification that includes all properties as defined in Section 5.2.1 of
             <xref target="RFC8007"/> as well as the additional properties required by the use cases
             listed below in <xref target="content-selection"/> and <xref target="trigger-extensibility"/>.
           </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="content-selection" title="Content Selection">
          <t>
             The trigger specification as defined in Section 5.2.1 of <xref target="RFC8007"/> provides means to
             select content objects by matching a full content URL or patterns with wildcards.
             This document specifies two additional selection options:
          </t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
             <t>
               Regular Expression - Using regex a uCDN can create more complex rules to select the
               content objects for the cases of "invalidation" and "purge". For example, purging specific
               content within a specific directory path.
             </t>
             <t>
               Content Playlist - Using video playlist files, a uCDN can trigger an operation that will
               be applied to a collection of distinct media files in a format that is natural for a
               streaming video content provider. A playlist may have several formats, specifically
               HTTP Live Streaming (HLS) *.m3u8 manifest <xref target="RFC8216"/>, Microsoft Smooth Streaming (MSS)
               *.ismc client manifest <xref target="MSS"/>, and Dynamic Adaptive Streaming over HTTP (DASH)
               *.mpd file <xref target="MPEG-DASH">[ISO/IEC 23009-1:2014]</xref>.
             </t>
          </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="trigger-extensibility" title="Trigger Extensibility">
          <t>
             The CDNI Control Interface / Triggers <xref target="RFC8007"/> defines a set of properties
             and objects used by the trigger commands. In this document we define an extension mechanism
             to the triggers interface that enables the application to add various functions that allow
             finer control over the trigger execution. This document specifies a generic trigger extension
             object wrapper for managing individual CDNI trigger extensions in an opaque manner.
          </t>

          <t>This document also registers CDNI Payload Types <xref target="RFC7736"/> under the namespace CIT
             for the initial set of trigger extension types:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>CIT.LocationPolicy (for controlling the locations in which the trigger is executed)</t>
              <t>CIT.TimePolicy (for scheduling a trigger to run in a specific time window)</t>
            </list>
          </t>


           <t>Example use cases<list style="symbols">
              <t>Pre-position with cache location policy</t>
              <t>Purge content with cache location policy</t>
              <t>Pre-position at a specific time</t>
              <t>Purge by content acquisition time (e.g. purge all content acquired in the past X hours)</t>
           </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="error-handling" title="Error Handling">
          <t>
             This document extends the CI/T Error Handling (see Section 4.7 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>) to support
             the following:
          </t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>
               Playlists and Regexs - report errors that happened due to specific playlists and/or regexs.
            </t>
            <t>
               Extension errors - report an error that happened due to an extension object.
            </t>
            <t>
               Error propagation - enable the uCDN to traceback an error to the dCDN in which it occurred.
            </t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="CDNI Footprint and Capabilities Interface Extensions">
        <t>
          Extending the trigger mechanism with optional properties requires the ability for the
          dCDN to advertise which optional properties it supports.
        </t>
        <t>
           The CDNI Footprint and Capabilities Interface <xref target="RFC8008"/> enables the dCDN to advertise the
           capabilities it supports across different footprints. This document introduces FCI objects to support the
           advertisement of these optional properties.
        </t>

        <t>Example use cases<list style="symbols">

          <t>Trigger types: Advertise which trigger types are supported by the dCDN.
             CDNI defines three trigger types (purge, invalidate, pre-position),
             but it does not necessarily mean that all dCDNs support all of them.
             The uCDN may prefer to work only with dCDN that support what the uCDN needs.</t>

          <t>Content selection rule types: Advertise which selection types are supported.
             For example, if adding content regex as a means to match on content URLs,
             not all dCDN would support it. For playlist mapping, advertise which types and versions
             of protocols are supported, e.g. HLS.vX/DASH.vY/MSS.vX, DASH templates.
             Note that the version string or schema are protocol specific.</t>

          <t>Trigger extensions: Advertise which trigger extensions object types are supported
             by the dCDN.</t>

        </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section  anchor="cit-version-v2" title="CI/T Version 2">
      <t>
         <xref target="RFC8007"/> does not define a version number and versioning scheme.
         We, therefore, designate the interface and objects as defined in Section 5 of
         <xref target="RFC8007"/> as version 1. The following sections define version 2 of
         the CI/T objects and their properties as extensions of version 1.
      </t>
      <section anchor="cit-objects-v2" title="CI/T Objects V2">
        <t>
           Version 2 of the CI/T interface requires the support of the following objects:
        </t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>
              CI/T Commands v2: A trigger command request using the payload type ci-trigger-command.v2.
              Version 2 MUST only use "trigger.v2" objects as defined in <xref target="trigger-spec-v2"/>,
              instead of "trigger" objects. All other properties of the trigger command v2 are as defined
              in Section 5.1.1 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>.
           </t>

           <t>
              Trigger Status Resource v2: A trigger status resource response using the payload type
              ci-trigger-status.v2. Version 2 MUST only use "trigger.v2" objects as defined in
              <xref target="trigger-spec-v2"/>, instead of a "trigger" object, as well as "errors.v2"
              array as defined in <xref target="error-description-v2"/>, instead of a "errors" array.
              All other properties of the trigger status v2 are as defined in Section 5.1.2 of
              <xref target="RFC8007"/>. The errors array "errors.v2" is a list of all errors that
              occurred in any of the downstream CDNs along the execution path. When a downstream CDN,
              dCDN-A, propagates a trigger to another downstream CDN, dCDN-B, it MUST also propagated
              back all errors reported by dCDN-B in the trigger status resource and add them to its
              own trigger status resource.
           </t>

           <t>
              Trigger Collections: The payload type ci-trigger-collection is used with no changes
              and as defined in 5.1.3 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>.
           </t>
        </list></t>
        <t>Usage example of version 2 of trigger command</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST:

    POST /triggers HTTP/1.1
    User-Agent: example-user-agent/0.1
    Host: triggers.dcdn.example.com
    Accept: */*
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-command.v2
    {
      "trigger.v2": { <properties of a trigger.v2 object> },
      "cdn-path": [ "AS64496:0" ]
    }

RESPONSE:

    HTTP/1.1 201 Created
    Date: Wed, 04 May 2016 08:48:10 GMT
    Content-Length: 467
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-status.v2
    Location: https://triggers.dcdn.example.com/triggers/0
    Server: example-server/0.1

    {
       "errors.v2": [ { <properties of 1st error.v2 object> },
                        ...,
                      { <properties of Nth error.v2 object> }
       ],
       "ctime": 1462351690,
       "etime": 1462351698,
       "mtime": 1462351690,
       "status": "pending",
       "trigger.v2": { <properties of a trigger.v2 object> }
    }
       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Usage example of version 2 of trigger status for the trigger created in the
           above trigger command example:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST:

    GET /triggers/0 HTTP/1.1
    User-Agent: example-user-agent/0.1
    Host: triggers.dcdn.example.com
    Accept: */*

RESPONSE:

    HTTP/1.1 200 OK
    Content-Length: 467
    Expires: Wed, 04 May 2016 08:49:10 GMT
    Server: example-server/0.1
    ETag: "6990548174277557683"
    Cache-Control: max-age=60
    Date: Wed, 04 May 2016 08:48:10 GMT
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-status.v2

    {
       "errors.v2": [ { <properties of 1st error.v2 object> },
                        ...,
                      { <properties of Nth error.v2 object> }
       ],
       "ctime": 1462351690,
       "etime": 1462351698,
       "mtime": 1462351690,
       "status": "pending",
       "trigger.v2": { <properties of a trigger.v2 object> }
    }

       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="error-handling-v2" title="Error Handling V2">
        <t>
           The CDNI CI/T interface defines a mechanism for error reporting (see Section 4.7 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>)
           and an Error Description object for reporting errors (see Section 5.2.6 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>).
           This document specifies version 2 of CI/T error handling in order to support the following:
        </t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>
             Extension errors - report an error that happened due to an extension object.
             As extension objects are expected to be added to the interface as new requirements
             comes along, it is expected that in some cases a dCDN may receive a trigger that it
             cannot process or does not understand. It is essential for the trigger caller to be
             able to understand when such errors occur so they can take actions to fix them.
             This document adds a mechanism to report extension errors.
          </t>
          <t>
             Error propagation - enable the uCDN to traceback an error to the dCDN in which it occurred.
             CDNI triggers may be propagated over a chain of downstream CDNs. Let us take for example an
             upstream (uCDN-A) CDN A that is delegating to a downstream CDN B (dCDN-B) and dCDN-B is delegating
             to a downstream CDN C (dCDN-C). Triggers sent from uCDN-A to dCDN-B may be redistributed
             from dCDN-B to dCDN-C and errors can happen anywhere along the path. Therefore, it is essential for
             uCDN-A that sets the trigger, to be able to trace back an error to the downstream CDN where it occurred.
             This document adds a mechanism to propagate the ID of the faulty dCDN back to the uCDN by adding the CDN ID
             to the error description. When a downstream dCDN-B propagates a trigger to another downstream
             dCDN-C, it MUST also propagate back the errors received in the trigger status resource from dCDN-C by adding
             them to the errors array in its own status resource to be sent back to the originating uCDN-A.
             This makes sure that the trigger originating upstream CDN will receive an array of errors that occurred
             in all the CDNs along the execution path, each error carrying its own CDN identifier.
          </t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="cit-objects-properties-v2" title="Properties of CI/T Version 2 objects">
        <t>
          This section defines the values that can appear in the top-level
          objects described in <xref target="cit-objects-v2"/>, and their encodings.
        </t>
        <section anchor="trigger-spec-v2" title="Trigger Specification Version 2 ">
          <t>
             Version 2 of the Trigger Specification adds the following properties on top
             of the existing properties of the trigger specification defined in Section
             5.2.1 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>.
          </t>

          <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Property: content.regexs<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: Regexs of content URLs to which the CI/T trigger command applies.</t>

              <t>Type: A JSON array of RegexMatch objects (see <xref target="regex-match"/>).</t>

              <t>Mandatory: No, but at least one of "metadata.*" or "content.*" MUST be present
                 and non-empty.</t>
            </list></t>

            <t>Property: content.playlists<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: Playlists of content the CI/T trigger command applies to.</t>

              <t>Type: A JSON array of Playlist objects (see <xref target="playlist"/>).</t>

              <t>Mandatory: No, but at least one of "metadata.*" or "content.*" MUST be present
                 and non-empty.</t>
            </list></t>

             <t>Property: extensions<list style="empty">

                <t>Description: Array of trigger extension data.</t>

                <t>Type: Array of GenericTriggerExtension objects (see <xref target="generic-extension-object"/>).</t>

                <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No. The default is no extensions.</t>
             </list></t>

          </list></t>

          <t>Example of an invalidation trigger.v2 with a list of regex objects, a list of playlist
             objects, and extensions:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "trigger.v2": {
    "type": "invalidate",
    "content.regexs": [ <list of RegexMatch objects> ],
    "content.playlists": [ <list of Playlist objects> ],
    "extensions": [ <list of GenericTriggerExtension objects ]
  },
  "cdn-path": [ "AS64496:0" ]
}

         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="regex-match" title="RegexMatch">
          <t>
             A RegexMatch consists of a regular expression string a URI is matched against,
             and flags describing the type of match. It is encoded as a JSON object with
             following properties:
          </t>

          <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Property: regex<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: A regular expression for URI matching. </t>

              <t>Type: A regular expression to match against the URI, i.e against the path-absolute
                 and the query string parameters <xref target="RFC3986"/>. The regular expression
                 string MUST be compatible with <xref target="PCRE841">PCRE</xref>.</t>

              <t>Note: Because '\' has special meaning in JSON <xref target="RFC8259"/> as the escape
                 character within JSON strings, the regular expression character '\' MUST be escaped as '\\'.</t>

              <t>Mandatory: Yes.</t>
            </list></t>
            <t>Property: case-sensitive<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: Flag indicating whether or not case-sensitive matching should be used. </t>

              <t>Type: JSON boolean. Either "true" (the matching is case sensitive) or "false"
                 (the matching is case insensitive).</t>

              <t>Mandatory: No; default is case-insensitive match (i.e., a value of "false").</t>
            </list></t>
            <t>Property: match-query-string<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: Flag indicating whether to include the query part of the URI when
                 comparing against the regex.</t>

              <t>Type: JSON boolean. Either "true" (the full URI, including the query part,
                 should be compared against the regex) or "false" (the query part of the URI
                 should be dropped before comparison with the given regex).</t>

              <t>Mandatory: No; default is "false".  The query part of the URI MUST be dropped
                 before comparison with the given regex. This makes the regular expression simpler
                 and safer for cases in which the query parameters are not relevant for the match.</t>
            </list></t>
          </list></t>

          <t>Example of a case sensitive, no query parameters, regex match against:</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
"^(https:\/\/video\.example\.com)\/([a-z])\/
 movie1\/([1-7])\/*(index.m3u8|\d{3}.ts)$"
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "regex": "^(https:\\/\\/video\\.example\\.com)\\/([a-z])\\/movie1\
           \/([1-7])\\/*(index.m3u8|\\d{3}.ts)$",
  "case-sensitive": true,
  "match-query-string": false
}

         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>This regex matches URLs of domain video.example.com  where the path structure is
             /(single lower case letter)/(name-of-title)/(single digit between 1 to 7)/(index.m3u8 or a 3 digit number with ts extension).
             For example:</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
https://video.example.com/d/movie1/5/index.m3u8
or
https://video.example.com/k/movie1/4/013.ts
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="playlist" title="Playlist">
          <t>A Playlist consists of a full URL and a media protocol identifier.
             An implementation that supports a specific playlist media protocol MUST be able to parse playlist
             files of that protocol type and extract, possibly recursively, the URLs to all media objects
             and/or sub playlist files, and apply the trigger to each one of them separately.</t>

          <t>Playlist is encoded as a JSON object with following properties:</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
             <t>Property: playlist<list style="empty">

               <t>Description: A URL to the playlist file.</t>

               <t>Type: A URL represented as a JSON string.</t>

               <t>Mandatory: Yes.</t>
             </list></t>
             <t>Property: media-protocol<list style="empty">

                <t>Description: Media protocol to be when parsing and interpreting this playlist. </t>

                <t>Type: MediaProtocol (see <xref target="media-protocol"/>).</t>

                <t>Mandatory: Yes.</t>
             </list></t>
          </list></t>
          <t>Example of a HLS playlist:</t>

           <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "playlist": "https://www.example.com/hls/title/index.m3u8",
  "media-protocol": "hls"
}

         ]]></artwork>
           </figure>

        </section>

        <section anchor="media-protocol" title="MediaProtocol">
          <t>Media Protocol objects are used to specify registered type of media protocol
             (see <xref target="IANA.CDNI.MediaProtocolReg"/>) used for protocol related
             operations like pre-position according to playlist.</t>
          <t>Type: JSON string</t>
          <t>Example:</t>
          <t>"dash"</t>
        </section>


        <section anchor="trigger-extensions" title="CI/T Trigger Extensions">
          <t>
            A "trigger.v2" object, as defined in <xref target="trigger-spec-v2"/> includes an
            optional array of trigger extension objects. A trigger extension contain properties
            that are used as directives for dCDN when executing the trigger command -- for example,
            location policies, time policies and so on. Each such CDNI Trigger extension is a specialization
            of a CDNI GenericTriggerExtension object. The GenericTriggerExtension object abstracts the basic
            information required for trigger distribution from the specifics of any given property
            (i.e., property semantics, enforcement options, etc.). All trigger extensions are optional,
            and it is thus the responsibility of the extension specification to define a consistent default
            behavior for the case the extension is not present.
          </t>

          <section anchor="enforcement-options" title="Enforcement Options">
           <t>
             The trigger enforcement options concept is in accordance with the metadata enforcement options
             as defined in Section 3.2 of <xref target="RFC8006"/>.
           </t>
           <t>
             The GenericTriggerExtension object defines the properties contained within it
             as well as whether or not the properties are "mandatory-to-enforce".
             If the dCDN does not understand or support a mandatory-to-enforce
             property, the dCDN MUST NOT execute the trigger command. If the extension is
             not mandatory-to-enforce, then that GenericTriggerExtension object can be
             safely ignored and the trigger command can be processed in accordance
             with the rest of the CDNI Trigger spec.
           </t>
           <t>
             Although a CDN MUST NOT execute a trigger command if a
             mandatory-to-enforce extension cannot be enforced, it could still be
             safe to redistribute that trigger (the "safe-to-redistribute"
             property) to another CDN without modification.  For example, in the
             cascaded CDN case, a transit CDN (tCDN) could convey
             mandatory-to-enforce trigger extension to a dCDN.  For a trigger extension
             that does not require customization or translation (i.e., trigger extension
             that is safe-to-redistribute), the data representation received off the wire
             MAY be stored and redistributed without being understood or supported
             by the tCDN.  However, for trigger extension that requires translation,
             transparent redistribution of the uCDN trigger values might not be
             appropriate.  Certain triggers extensions can be safely, though perhaps not
             optimally, redistributed unmodified.  For example, pre-position command might
             be executed in suboptimal times for some geographies if transparently
             redistributed, but it might still work.
           </t>
           <t>
             Redistribution safety MUST be specified for each GenericTriggerExtension
             property. If a CDN does not understand or support a given
             GenericTriggerExtension property that is not safe-to-redistribute, the CDN
             MUST set the "incomprehensible" flag to true for that GenericTriggerExtension
             object before redistributing it.  The "incomprehensible"
             flag signals to a dCDN that trigger metadata was not properly transformed
             by the tCDN.  A CDN MUST NOT attempt to execute a trigger that has been
             marked as "incomprehensible" by a uCDN.
           </t>
           <t>
             tCDNs MUST NOT change the value of mandatory-to-enforce or
             safe-to-redistribute when propagating a trigger to a dCDN.  Although a
             tCDN can set the value of "incomprehensible" to true, a tCDN MUST NOT
             change the value of "incomprehensible" from true to false.
           </t>
           <t>
             <xref target="tcdn-actions"/> describes the action to be taken by a tCDN for the
             different combinations of mandatory-to-enforce ("MtE") and safe-to-redistribute
             ("StR") properties when the tCDN either does or does not understand the trigger
             extension object in question:
           </t>

           <texttable anchor="tcdn-actions" title="Action to be taken by a tCDN for the different combinations of MtE and StR properties">
             <ttcol align="left">MtE</ttcol>
             <ttcol align="left">StR</ttcol>
             <ttcol align="left">Extension object understood by tCDN</ttcol>
             <ttcol align="left">Trigger action</ttcol>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>Can execute and redistribute.</c>

               <c>False</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>Can execute and redistribute.</c>

               <c>False</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>Can execute. MUST set "incomprehensible" to true when redistributing.</c>

               <c>False</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>Can execute. Can redistribute after transforming the trigger extension
                  (if the CDN knows how to do so safely); otherwise, MUST set
                  "incomprehensible" to true when redistributing.</c>

               <c>True</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>Can execute and redistribute.</c>

               <c>True</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>MUST NOT execute but can redistribute..</c>

               <c>True</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>Can execute. Can redistribute after transforming the trigger extension
                  (if the CDN knows how to do so safely); otherwise, MUST set
                  "incomprehensible" to true when redistributing.</c>

               <c>True</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>MUST NOT serve.  MUST set "incomprehensible" to true when redistributing.</c>

           </texttable>

           <t>
             <xref target="dcdn-actions"/> describes the action to be taken by a tCDN for the different
             combinations of mandatory-to-enforce and "incomprehensible" ("Incomp")
             properties, when the dCDN either does or does not understand
             the trigger extension object in question:
           </t>

           <texttable anchor="dcdn-actions" title="Action to be taken by a dCDN for the different combinations of MtE and Incomp properties">
             <ttcol align="left">MtE</ttcol>
             <ttcol align="left">Incomp</ttcol>
             <ttcol align="left">Extension object understood by dCDN</ttcol>
             <ttcol align="left">Trigger action</ttcol>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>Can execute.</c>

               <c>False</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>Can execute but MUST NOT interpret/apply any trigger extension marked as "incomprehensible".</c>

               <c>False</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>Can execute.</c>

               <c>False</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>Can execute but MUST NOT interpret/apply any trigger extension marked as "incomprehensible".</c>

               <c>True</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>Can execute.</c>

               <c>True</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>MUST NOT execute.</c>

               <c>True</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>MUST NOT execute.</c>

               <c>True</c>
               <c>True</c>
               <c>False</c>
               <c>MUST NOT execute.</c>

           </texttable>

          </section>

          <section anchor="generic-extension-object" title="GenericExtensionObject">
            <t>A GenericTriggerExtension object is a wrapper for managing individual CDNI
               Trigger extensions in an opaque manner.</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
              <t>Property: generic-trigger-extension-type<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: Case-insensitive CDNI Trigger extension object type.</t>

                 <t>Type: String containing the CDNI Payload Type <xref target="RFC7736"/> of the object contained
                    in the generic-trigger-extension-value property (see table in <xref target="IANA.CDNI.payload"/>).</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: Yes.</t>
              </list></t>

              <t>Property: generic-trigger-extension-value<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: CDNI Trigger extension object.</t>

                 <t>Type: Format/Type is defined by the value of the
                    generic-trigger-extension-type property above.</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: Yes.</t>
              </list></t>

              <t>Property: mandatory-to-enforce<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: Flag identifying whether or not the enforcement of
                    this trigger extension is mandatory.</t>

                 <t>Type: Boolean</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No.  Default is to treat the trigger extension as
                    mandatory-to-enforce (i.e., a value of True).</t>
              </list></t>

              <t>Property: safe-to-redistribute<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: Flag identifying whether or not this trigger extension
                    can be safely redistributed without modification.</t>

                 <t>Type: Boolean</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No.  Default is to allow transparent
                    redistribution (i.e., a value of True).</t>
              </list></t>

              <t>Property: incomprehensible<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: Flag identifying whether or not any CDN in the
                    chain of delegation has failed to understand and/or failed to
                    properly transform this trigger extension object.  Note: This flag only
                    applies to trigger extension objects whose safe-to-redistribute property
                    has a value of False.</t>

                 <t>Type: Boolean</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No.  Default is comprehensible (i.e., a
                    value of False).</t>
              </list></t>

            </list></t>
            <t>Example of a GenericTriggerExtension containing a specific trigger extension object:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[

{
  "generic-trigger-extension-type":
     <Type of this trigger extension object>,
  "generic-trigger-extension-value":
      {
        <properties of this trigger extension object>
      },
  "mandatory-to-enforce": true,
  "safe-to-redistribute": true,
  "incomprehensible": false
}

       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="error-description-v2" title="Error Description Version 2">
          <t>
             Version 2 of the Error Description adds the "content.playlists", "content.regexs", "extensions" and "cdn"
             properties on top of the existing properties of version 1 of the trigger Error Description as defined in
             Section 5.2.6 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>.
          </t>

          <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Properties: content.regexs, content.playlists<list style="empty">
              <t>
                Description: Content Regex and Playlist references copied from the Trigger Specification.
                Only those regexs and playlists to which the error applies are included in each property,
                but those references MUST be exactly as they appear in the request; the dCDN MUST NOT change
                or generalize the URLs or Regexs. Note that these properties are added on top of the already
                existing properties: "metadata.urls", "content.urls", "metadata.patterns" and "content.patterns".
              </t>
              <t>
                Type: A JSON array of JSON strings, where each string is copied from a "content.regexs" or
                "content.playlists" value in the corresponding Trigger Specification.
              </t>
              <t>
                Mandatory: At least one of "content.regexs", "content.playlists", "metadata.urls", "content.urls",
                "metadata.patterns" or "content.patterns" is mandatory in each Error Description object.
              </t>
            </list></t>
            <t>Property: extensions<list style="empty">
              <t>
                Description: Array of trigger extension objects copied from the corresponding "extensions" array
                from the Trigger Specification. Only those extensions to which the error applies are included, but
                those extensions MUST be exactly as they appear in the request.
                where each object is copied from data copied from the
              </t>

              <t>
                Type: Array of GenericTriggerExtension objects, where each extension object is copied
                from the "extensions" array values in the Trigger Specification.
              </t>

              <t>
                Mandatory: No. The "extensions" array SHOULD be used only if there were errors related to
                extension objects.
              </t>
            </list></t>
            <t>Property: cdn<list style="empty">
              <t>
                Description: The CDN PID of the CDN where the error occurred. The "cdn" property is used
                by the originating uCDN or by propagating dCDN in order to distinguish in which CDN the
                error occured.
              </t>

              <t>Type: A non-empty JSON string, where the string is a CDN PID as defined in Section
                 4.6 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>.</t>

              <t>Mandatory: Yes.</t>
            </list></t>
          </list></t>

          <t>Example of an Error Description object reporting a malformed Playlist:
          </t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[

{
   "content.playlists": [
      {
        "playlist": "https://www.example.com/hls/title/index.m3u8",
        "media-protocol": "hls"
      }
    ],
   "description": "Failed to parse HLS playlist",
   "error": "econtent",
   "cdn": "AS64500:0"
},
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>Example of an Error Description object reporting an unsupported extension object:
          </t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "errors.v2": [
   {
     "extensions": [
        {
          "generic-trigger-extension-type":
             <Type of this erroneous trigger extension object>,
          "generic-trigger-extension-value":
              {
                <properties of this erroneous trigger extension object>
              },
        }
      ],
     "description": "unrecognized extension <type>",
     "error": "eextension",
     "cdn": "AS64500:0"
   },
  ]
}
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="error-code" title="Error codes">
          <t>
             This document adds the error code "eextension" to the error codes table defined in Section
             5.2.6 of <xref target="RFC8007"/>. This error code designates that an error occurred while
             parsing a generic trigger extension, or that the specific extension is not supported by the CDN.
             A CDN that fails to parse or execute a generic extension object MUST report it using the "errors.v2"
             array within the trigger status resource, while setting the error code to "eextension" and providing
             an appropriate description. The "eextension" error code is a registered type of
             "CDNI CI/T Trigger Error Codes" (see <xref target="IANA.CDNI.CIT.ErrorCodes"/>).
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>
      <section anchor="interface-examples" title="Examples">
        <t>
          The following subsections provides usage examples of the specified interface extensions being used
          by the trigger command and status resource.
        </t>
        <section anchor="invalidate-with-regex" title="Invalidation with Regex">
          <t>
            In the following example a CI/T "invalidate" command uses the Regex property to specify the range of
            content objects for invalidation, the command is rejected by the dCDN due to regex complexity, and
            an appropriate error is reflected in the status response.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST:

    POST /triggers HTTP/1.1
    User-Agent: example-user-agent/0.1
    Host: triggers.dcdn.example.com
    Accept: */*
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-command.v2
    {
      "trigger.v2": {
        "type": "invalidate",
        "content.regexs": [
          {
            "regex": "^(https:\\/\\/video\\.example\\.com)\\/
            ([a-z])\\/movie1\\/([1-7])\\/*(index.m3u8|\\d{3}.ts)$",
            "case-sensitive": true,
            "match-query-string": false
          },
          { <RegexMatch #2> },
          ...
          { <RegexMatch #N> },
        ],
      },
      "cdn-path": [ "AS64496:0" ]
    }

RESPONSE:

    HTTP/1.1 201 Created
    Date: Wed, 04 May 2016 08:48:10 GMT
    Content-Length: 467
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-status.v2
    Location: https://triggers.dcdn.example.com/triggers/0
    Server: example-server/0.1

    {
       "errors.v2": [
         {
           "content.regexs": [
              {
                "regex": "^(https:\\/\\/video\\.example\\.com)\\/
                ([a-z])\\/movie1\\/([1-7])\\/*(index.m3u8|\\d{3}.ts)$",
                "case-sensitive": true,
                "match-query-string": false
              },
            ],
           "description": "The dCDN rejected a regex due to complexity",
           "error": "ereject",
           "cdn": "AS64500:0"
         },
       ],
       "ctime": 1462351690,
       "etime": 1462351698,
       "mtime": 1462351690,
       "status": "failed",
       "trigger.v2": { <content of trigger object from the command> }
    }
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="preposition-with-playlists" title="Preposition with Playlists">
          <t>
            In the following example a CI/T "preposition" command uses the Playlist property to specify the full
            media library of a specific content. The command fails due to playlist parse error and an appropriate
            error is reflected in the status response.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST:

    POST /triggers HTTP/1.1
    User-Agent: example-user-agent/0.1
    Host: triggers.dcdn.example.com
    Accept: */*
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-command.v2
    {
      "trigger.v2": {
        "type": "preposition",
        "content.playlists": [
         {
          "playlist": "https://www.example.com/hls/title/index.m3u8",
          "media-protocol": "hls"
         },
         { <Playlist #2> },
         ...
         { <Playlist #N> },
        ],
      },
      "cdn-path": [ "AS64496:0" ]
    }

RESPONSE:

    HTTP/1.1 201 Created
    Date: Wed, 04 May 2016 08:48:10 GMT
    Content-Length: 467
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-status.v2
    Location: https://triggers.dcdn.example.com/triggers/0
    Server: example-server/0.1

    {
      "errors.v2": [
       {
         "content.playlists": [
          {
            "playlist": "https://www.example.com/hls/title/index.m3u8",
            "media-protocol": "hls"
          },
         ],
         "description": "The dCDN was not able to parse the playlist",
         "error": "econtent",
         "cdn": "AS64500:0"
       },
      ],
      "ctime": 1462351690,
      "etime": 1462351698,
      "mtime": 1462351690,
      "status": "failed",
      "trigger.v2": { <content of trigger object from the command> }
    }
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="trigger-with-extensions" title="Extensions with Error Propagation">
          <t>
            In the following example a CI/T "preposition" command is using two extensions to control the
            way the trigger is executed. In this example the receiving dCDN identified as "AS64500:0"
            does not support the first extension in the extensions array. dCDN "AS64500:0" further
            distributes this trigger to another downstream CDN that is identified as "AS64501:0", which
            does not support the second extension in the extensions array. The error is propagate from
            "AS64501:0" to "AS64500:0" and the errors.v2 array reflects both errors.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
REQUEST:

    POST /triggers HTTP/1.1
    User-Agent: example-user-agent/0.1
    Host: triggers.dcdn.example.com
    Accept: */*
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-command.v2
    {
      "trigger.v2": {
        "type": "preposition",
        "content.playlists": [
         {
           "playlist": "https://www.example.com/hls/title/index.m3u8",
           "media-protocol": "hls"
         },
        ],
        "extensions": [
            {
              "generic-trigger-extension-type":
                 <Type of trigger extension object #1>,
              "generic-trigger-extension-value":
                  {
                    <properties of trigger extension object #1>
                  },
              "mandatory-to-enforce": false,
              "safe-to-redistribute": true,
            },
            {
              "generic-trigger-extension-type":
                 <Type of trigger extension object #2>,
              "generic-trigger-extension-value":
                  {
                    <properties of trigger extension object #2>
                  },
              "mandatory-to-enforce": false,
              "safe-to-redistribute": true,
            },
        ],
      },
      "cdn-path": [ "AS64496:0" ]
    }

RESPONSE:

    HTTP/1.1 201 Created
    Date: Wed, 04 May 2016 08:48:10 GMT
    Content-Length: 467
    Content-Type: application/cdni; ptype=ci-trigger-status.v2
    Location: https://triggers.dcdn.example.com/triggers/0
    Server: example-server/0.1

    {
       "errors.v2": [
         {
           "extensions": [
              {
                "generic-trigger-extension-type":
                   <Type of trigger extension object #1>,
                "generic-trigger-extension-value":
                    {
                      <properties of trigger extension object #1>
                    },
                "mandatory-to-enforce": false,
                "safe-to-redistribute": true,
              },
            ],
           "description": "unrecognized extension <type>",
           "error": "eextension",
           "cdn": "AS64500:0"
         },
         {
           "extensions": [
              {
                "generic-trigger-extension-type":
                   <Type of trigger extension object #2>,
                "generic-trigger-extension-value":
                    {
                      <properties of trigger extension object #2>
                    },
                "mandatory-to-enforce": false,
                "safe-to-redistribute": true,
              },
            ],
           "description": "unrecognized extension <type>",
           "error": "eextension",
           "cdn": "AS64501:0"
         },
       ],
       "ctime": 1462351690,
       "etime": 1462351698,
       "mtime": 1462351690,
       "status": "failed",
       "trigger.v2": { <content of trigger object from the command> }
    }
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section anchor="trigger-extension-objects" title="Trigger Extension Objects">
      <t>The objects defined below are intended to be used in the GenericTriggerExtension
         object's generic-trigger-extension-value field as defined in Section
         <xref target="generic-extension-object"/>, and their generic-trigger-extension-type
         property MUST be set to the appropriate CDNI Payload Type as defined in <xref target="IANA.CDNI.payload"/> .
      </t>

      <section anchor="location-policy" title="LocationPolicy extension">
        <t>A content operation may be relevant for a specific geographical region, or need to
           be excluded from a specific region. In this case, the trigger should be applied
           only to parts of the network that are either "included" or "not excluded" by the location policy.
           Note that the restrictions here are on the cache location rather than the client location.</t>

        <t>The LocationPolicy object defines which CDN or cache locations for which the trigger
           command is relevant.</t>

        <t>Example use cases:<list style="symbols">

            <t>Pre-position: Certain contracts allow for pre-positioning or availability
               of contract in all regions except for certain excluded regions in the world,
               including caches. For example, some content cannot ever knowingly touch
               servers in a specific country, including cached content. Therefore, these regions
               MUST be excluded from a pre-positioning operation.</t>

            <t>Purge: In certain cases, content may have been located on servers in regions
               where the content must not reside. In such cases a purge operation to
               remove content specifically from that region, is required.</t>

        </list></t>

        <t>Object specification<list style="empty">

              <t>Property: locations<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: An Access List that allows or denies (blocks) the trigger execution
                    per cache location.</t>

                 <t>Type: Array of LocationRule objects (see Section 4.2.2.1 of <xref target="RFC8006"/>)</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: Yes.</t>
              </list></t>
        </list></t>

        <t>
           If a location policy object is not listed within the trigger command, the default behavior is to
           execute the trigger in all available caches and locations of the dCDN.
        </t>
        <t>
           The trigger command is allowed, or denied, for a specific cache location according to the
           action of the first location whose footprint matches against that cache's location.
           If two or more footprints overlap, the first footprint that matches against the cache's location
           determines the action a CDN MUST take. If the "locations" property is an empty list or if none of
           the listed footprints match the location of a specific cache location, then the result is equivalent
           to a "deny" action.
        </t>


        <t>The following is an example of generic trigger extension object containing a location policy
           object that allows the trigger execution in the US but blocks its execution in Canada:
        </t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
   "generic-trigger-extension-type": "CIT.LocationPolicy",
   "generic-trigger-extension-value":
    {
       "locations": [
         {
           "action": "allow",
           "footprints": [
             {
               "footprint-type": "countrycode",
               "footprint-value": ["us"]
             }
           ]
         },
         {
           "action": "deny",
           "footprints": [
             {
               "footprint-type": "countrycode",
               "footprint-value": ["ca"]
             }
           ]
         }
       ]
    },
   "mandatory-to-enforce": true,
   "safe-to-redistribute": true,
   "incomprehensible": false
}
       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="time-policy" title="TimePolicy Extension">
        <t>A uCDN may wish to perform content management operations on the dCDN in a specific schedule.
           The TimePolicy extensions allows the uCDN to instruct the dCDN to execute the trigger command
           in a desired time window. For example, a content provider that wishes to pre-populate a new
           episode at off-peak time so that it would be ready on caches at prime time when the episode
           is released for viewing. A scheduled operation enables the uCDN to direct the dCDN in what
           time frame to execute the trigger.
        </t>
        <t>
           A uCDN may wish to to schedule a trigger such that the dCDN will execute it in local time,
           as it is measured in each region. For example, a uCDN may wish the dCDN to pull the content
           at off-peak hours, between 2AM-4AM, however, as a CDN is distributed across multiple time
           zones, the UTC definition of 2AM depends on the actual location.
        </t>
        <t>We define two alternatives for localized scheduling:<list style="symbols">
           <t>Regional schedule: When used in conjunction with the Location Policy defined
              in <xref target="location-policy"/>, the uCDN can trigger separate commands for
              different geographical regions, for each region using a different schedule. This allows
              the uCDN to control the execution time per region.
           </t>
           <t>Local Time schedule: We introduce a "local time" version for Internet timestamps
              that follows the notation for local time as defined in Section 4.2.2 of <xref target="ISO8601"/>.
              When local time is used, that dCDN SHOULD execute the triggers at different absolute times,
              according the local time of each execution location.
           </t>
        </list></t>

         <t>Object specification<list style="empty">

              <t>Property: unix-time-window<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: A UNIX epoch time window in which the trigger SHOULD be executed.</t>

                 <t>Type: TimeWindow object using UNIX epoch timestamps (see Section 4.2.3.2 of
                    <xref target="RFC8006"/>)
                 </t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No, but exactly one of "unix-time-window", "utc-window"
                    or "local-time-window" MUST be present.</t>
              </list></t>
              <t>Property: utc-window<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: A UTC time window in which the trigger SHOULD be executed.</t>

                 <t>Type: UTCWindow object as defined in <xref target="utc-window"/>.</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No, but exactly one of "unix-time-window", "utc-window"
                    or "local-time-window" MUST be present.</t>
              </list></t>
              <t>Property: local-time-window<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: A local time window. The dCDN SHOULD execute the trigger at the
                    defined time frame, interpreted as the the local time per location.
                 </t>

                 <t>Type: LocalTimeWindow object as defined in <xref target="local-time-window"/>.</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No, but exactly one of "unix-time-window", "utc-window"
                    or "local-time-window" MUST be present.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>

          <t>
             If a time policy object is not listed within the trigger command, the default behavior
             is to execute the trigger in a time frame most suitable to the dCDN taking under consideration
             other constrains and / or obligations.
          </t>

        <t>Example of a generic trigger extension object containing a time policy object that schedules the
           trigger execution to a window between 09:00 01/01/2000 UTC and 17:00 01/01/2000 UTC, using
           the "unix-time-window" property:
        </t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
{
   "generic-trigger-extension-type": "CIT.TimePolicy",
   "generic-trigger-extension-value":
    {
      "unix-time-window": {
         "start": 946717200,
         "end": 946746000
      }
    }
   "mandatory-to-enforce": true,
   "safe-to-redistribute": true,
   "incomprehensible": false
}
       ]]></artwork>
       </figure>

        <section anchor="utc-window" title="UTCWindow">
          <t>
             A UTCWindow object describes a time range in UTC or UTC and a zone offset that can
             be applied by a TimePolicy.
          </t>
          <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Property: start<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: The start time of the window.</t>

              <t>Type: Internet date and time as defined in <xref target="RFC3339"/>.</t>

              <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: Yes.</t>
            </list></t>
            <t>Property: end<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: The end time of the window.</t>

              <t>Type: Internet date and time as defined in <xref target="RFC3339"/>.</t>

              <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: Yes.</t>
            </list></t>
         </list></t>

         <t>
           Example UTCWindow object that describes a time window from 02:30
           01/01/2000 UTC to 04:30 01/01/2000 UTC:
         </t>

         <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "start": 2000-01-01T02:30:00.00Z,
  "end": 2000-01-01T04:30:00.00Z,
}
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

         <t>
           Example UTCWindow object that describes a time window in New York time zone offset
           UTC-05:00 from 02:30 01/01/2000 to 04:30 01/01/2000:
         </t>

         <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "start": 2000-01-01T02:30:00.00-05:00,
  "end": 2000-01-01T04:30:00.00-05:00,
}
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="local-time-window" title="LocalTimeWindow">
          <t>
             A LocalTimeWindow object describes a time range in local time. The reader of this
             object MUST interpret it as "the local time at the location of execution". For example,
             if the time window states 2AM to 4AM local time then a dCDN that has presence in
             both London (UTC) and New York (UTC-05:00) will execute the trigger at 2AM-4AM UTC
             in London and at 2AM-4AM UTC-05:00 in New York.
          </t>
          <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Property: start<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: The start time of the window.</t>

              <t>Type: JSON string formatted as DateLocalTime as defined in
                 <xref target="date-local-time"/>.
              </t>

              <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: Yes.</t>
            </list></t>
            <t>Property: end<list style="empty">

              <t>Description: The end time of the window.</t>

              <t>Type: JSON string formatted as DateLocalTime as defined in
                 <xref target="date-local-time"/>.
              </t>

              <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: Yes.</t>
            </list></t>
         </list></t>

         <t>
           Example LocalTimeWindow object that describes a local time window from 02:30
           01/01/2000 to 04:30 01/01/2000.
         </t>

         <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
{
  "start": 2000-01-01T02:30:00.00,
  "end": 2000-01-01T04:30:00.00,
}
         ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="date-local-time" title="DateLocalTime">
          <t>
            DateLocalTime is a timestamp that follows the date and local time notation in Section 4.3.2
            of <xref target="ISO8601"/> as a complete date and time extended representation,
            where the time zone designator is omitted. In addition, for simplicity and as exact accuracy
            is not an objective in this case, this specification does not support the decimal fractions of
            seconds, and does not take leap second into consideration.
          </t>
          <t>
             Type: JSON string using the format "date-local-time" as defined in <xref target="date-local-time-format"/>.
          </t>
          <section anchor="date-local-time-format" title="Date and Local Time Format">
            <t>
              The Date and Local Time format is specified here using the syntax description
              notation defined in <xref target="ABNF"/>.
            </t>
<figure>
  <artwork>
date-fullyear   = 4DIGIT
date-month      = 2DIGIT  ; 01-12
date-mday       = 2DIGIT  ; 01-28, 01-29, 01-30, 01-31 based on
                          ; month/year
time-hour       = 2DIGIT  ; 00-23
time-minute     = 2DIGIT  ; 00-59
time-second     = 2DIGIT  ; 00-59 leap seconds are not supported

local-time      = time-hour ":" time-minute ":" time-second
full-date       = date-fullyear "-" date-month "-" date-mday
date-local-time = full-date "T" local-time
  </artwork>
</figure>

            <t>Example time representing 09:00AM on 01/01/2000 local time:</t>
            <t>2000-01-01T09:00:00.00</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
              <t>
                NOTE: Per <xref target="ABNF"/> and <xref target="ISO8601"/>, the "T" character
                in this syntax may alternatively be lower case "t". For simplicity,
                Applications that generate the "date-local-time" format defined here,
                SHOULD only use the upper case letter "T".
              </t>
            </list></t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="date-local-time-restrictions" title="Restrictions">
            <t>
               The grammar element date-mday represents the day number within the
               current month.  The maximum value varies based on the month and year
               as follows:
            </t>
<figure>
  <artwork>
Month Number  Month/Year           Maximum value of date-mday
------------  ----------           --------------------------
01            January              31
02            February, normal     28
02            February, leap year  29
03            March                31
04            April                30
05            May                  31
06            June                 30
07            July                 31
08            August               31
09            September            30
10            October              31
11            November             30
12            December             31
  </artwork>
</figure>
            <t>
               See Appendix C of <xref target="RFC3339"/> for a sample C code that determines if a year is
               a leap year.
            </t>
            <t>
               The grammar element time-second may have the values 0-59. The value of 60 that is used in
               <xref target="ISO8601"/> to represent a leap second MUST NOT be used.
            </t>
            <t>
               Although <xref target="ISO8601"/> permits the hour to be "24", this profile of <xref target="ISO8601"/>
               only allows values between "00" and "23" for the hour in order to reduce confusion.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="footprint-and-capabilities" title="Footprint and Capabilities">
      <t>
        This section covers the FCI objects required for advertisement of the extensions and properties
        introduced in this document.
      </t>
      <section title="CI/T Versions Capability Object">
        <t>
           The CI/T versions capability object is used to indicate support for one or more CI/T objects versions.
           Note that the default version as originally defined in <xref target="RFC8007"/> MUST be implicitly
           supported regardless of the versions listed in this capability object.
        </t>

        <t><list style="empty">
           <t>Property: versions<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: A list of version numbers.</t>

                 <t>Type: An array of JSON strings</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No. The default is version 1. A missing or an empty versions list
                    means that  only version 1 of the interface and objects is supported.</t>
           </list></t>
        </list></t>
        <section anchor="versions-capability-object" title="CI/T Versions Capability Object Serialization">
          <t>
             The following shows an example of CI/T Versions Capability object serialization for a dCDN that supports
             versions 2 and 2.1 of the CI/T interface.
          </t>

          <figure>
           <artwork><![CDATA[

{
 "capabilities": [
   {
     "capability-type": "FCI.TriggerVersion",
     "capability-value": {
       "versions": [ "1", "2", "2.1" ]
     },
     "footprints": [
       <Footprint objects>
     ]
   }
 ]
}
        ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="CI/T Playlist Protocol Capability Object">
        <t>
           The CI/T Playlist Protocol capability object is used to indicate support for one or more
           MediaProtocol types listed in <xref target="IANA.CDNI.MediaProtocolReg"/> by the playlists
           property of the "trigger.v2" object.
        </t>

        <t><list style="empty">
           <t>Property: media-protocols<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: A list of media protocols.</t>

                 <t>Type: A list of MediaProtocol (from the CDNI Triggers media protocol types
                    <xref target="IANA.CDNI.MediaProtocolReg"/>)</t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No. The default, in case of a missing or an empty list,
                    is none supported.</t>
           </list></t>
        </list></t>
        <section anchor="playlist-protocol-capability-object" title="CI/T Playlist Protocol Capability Object Serialization">
          <t>
             The following shows an example of CI/T Playlist Protocol Capability object serialization
             for a dCDN that supports "hls" and "dash".
          </t>

          <figure>
           <artwork><![CDATA[

{
 "capabilities": [
   {
     "capability-type": "FCI.TriggerPlaylistProtocol",
     "capability-value": {
       "media-protocols": ["hls", "dash"]
     },
     "footprints": [
       <Footprint objects>
     ]
   }
 ]
}
        ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="CI/T Trigger Extension Capability Object">
        <t>
           The CI/T Generic Extension capability object is used to indicate support for one or more
           GenericExtensionObject types.
        </t>

        <t><list style="empty">
           <t>Property: trigger-extension<list style="empty">

                 <t>Description: A list of supported CDNI CI/T GenericExtensionObject types.</t>

                 <t>Type: List of strings corresponding to entries from the "CDNI Payload Types" registry
                    <xref target="RFC7736"/> that are under the CIT namespace, and that correspond to CDNI
                    CI/T GenericExtensionObject objects.
                 </t>

                 <t>Mandatory-to-Specify: No. The default, in case of a missing or an empty list, MUST be
                    interpreted as "no GenericExtensionObject types are supported". A non-empty list MUST be
                    interpreted as containing "the only GenericExtensionObject types that are supported".
                 </t>
           </list></t>
        </list></t>
        <section anchor="trigger-extension-capability-object" title="CI/T Trigger Extension Capability Object Serialization">
          <t>
             The following shows an example of CI/T Trigger Extension Capability object serialization for
             a dCDN that supports the "CIT.LocationPolicy" and the "CIT.TimePolicy" objects.
          </t>

          <figure>
           <artwork><![CDATA[

{
 "capabilities": [
   {
     "capability-type": "FCI.TriggerGenericExtension",
     "capability-value": {
       "trigger-extension": ["CIT.LocationPolicy", "CIT.TimePolicy"]
     },
     "footprints": [
       <Footprint objects>
     ]
   }
 ]
}
        ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.payload" title="CDNI Payload Types">

        <t>This document requests the registration of the following CDNI
           Payload Types under the IANA "CDNI Payload Types" registry defined in <xref target="RFC7736"/>:</t>


        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left">Payload Type</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Specification</ttcol>

          <c>ci-trigger-command.v2</c>
          <c>RFCthis</c>

          <c>ci-trigger-status.v2</c>
          <c>RFCthis</c>

          <c>CIT.LocationPolicy</c>
          <c>RFCthis</c>

          <c>CIT.TimePolicy</c>
          <c>RFCthis</c>

          <c>FCI.TriggerVersion</c>
          <c>RFCthis</c>

          <c>FCI.TriggerPlaylistProtocol</c>
          <c>RFCthis</c>

          <c>FCI.TriggerGenericExtension</c>
          <c>RFCthis</c>
       </texttable>

        <t>[RFC Editor: Please replace RFCthis with the published RFC
        number for this document.]</t>

         <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.payload.ci-trigger-command.v2" title="CDNI ci-trigger-command.v2 Payload Type">
          <t>Purpose: The purpose of this payload type is to distinguish version 2 of the CI/T command
            (and any associated capability advertisement)</t>
          <t>Interface: CI/T</t>
          <t>Encoding: see <xref target="cit-objects-v2"/></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.payload.ci-trigger-status.v2" title="CDNI ci-trigger-status.v2 Payload Type">
          <t>Purpose: The purpose of this payload type is to distinguish version 2 of the CI/T status resource response
            (and any associated capability advertisement)</t>
          <t>Interface: CI/T</t>
          <t>Encoding: see <xref target="cit-objects-v2"/></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.payload.CIT.LocationPolicy" title="CDNI CI/T LocationPolicy Trigger Extension Type">
          <t>Purpose: The purpose of this Trigger Extension type is to distinguish LocationPolicy CIT Trigger Extension objects.</t>
          <t>Interface: CI/T</t>
          <t>Encoding: see <xref target="location-policy"/></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.payload.CIT.TimePolicy" title="CDNI CI/T TimePolicy Trigger Extension Type">
          <t>Purpose: The purpose of this Trigger Extension type is to distinguish TimePolicy CI/T Trigger Extension objects.</t>
          <t>Interface: CI/T</t>
          <t>Encoding: see <xref target="time-policy"/></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.payload.FCI.TriggersVersions" title="CDNI FCI CI/T Versions Payload Type">
          <t>Purpose: The purpose of this payload type is to distinguish FCI advertisement objects for
             CI/T Triggers Versions objects</t>
          <t>Interface: FCI</t>
          <t>Encoding: see <xref target="versions-capability-object"/></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.payload.FCI.PlaylistProtocol" title="CDNI FCI CI/T Playlist Protocol Payload Type">
          <t>Purpose: The purpose of this payload type is to distinguish FCI advertisement objects for
             CI/T Playlist Protocol objects</t>
          <t>Interface: FCI</t>
          <t>Encoding: see <xref target="playlist-protocol-capability-object"/></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.payload.FCI.ExtensionObject" title="CDNI FCI CI/T Extension Objects Payload Type">
          <t>Purpose: The purpose of this payload type is to distinguish FCI advertisement objects for
             CI/T Extension objects</t>
          <t>Interface: FCI</t>
          <t>Encoding: see <xref target="trigger-extension-capability-object"/></t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.CIT.ErrorCodes" title="CDNI CI/T Trigger Error Codes types">
        <t>The IANA is requested to update the "CDNI CI/T Error Codes" subregistry (defined in Section 7.3 of
           <xref target="RFC8007"/> and located at <eref target = "https://www.iana.org/assignments/cdni-parameters"/>)
           with the following registration:</t>
        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left">Error Code</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Specification</ttcol>
            <c>eextension</c>
            <c>The dCDN failed to parse a generic extension object, or does not support this extension.</c>
            <c>Section <xref target="error-code"/> of this document.</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section anchor="IANA.CDNI.MediaProtocolReg" title="CDNI Media protocol types">
        <t>The IANA is requested to create a new "CDNI MediaProtocol Types" subregistry
           in the "Content Delivery Networks Interconnection (CDNI) Parameters" registry.
           The "CDNI MediaProtocol Types" namespace defines the valid MediaProtocol object
           values in Section <xref target="media-protocol"/>, used by the Playlist object.
           Additions to the MediaProtocol namespace conform to the "Specification Required"
           policy as defined in Section 4.6 of <xref target="RFC8126"/>,  where the specification
           defines the MediaProtocol Type and the protocol to which it is associated.
           The designated expert will verify that new protocol definitions do not duplicate
           existing protocol definitions and prevent gratuitous additions to the namespace.</t>

        <t>The following table defines the initial MediaProtocol values corresponding
           to the HLS, MSS, and DASH protocols:</t>
        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left">MediaProtocol Type</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Specification</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Protocol Specification</ttcol>
            <c>hls</c>
            <c>HTTP Live Streaming</c>
            <c>RFCthis</c>
            <c><xref target="RFC8216">RFC 8216</xref></c>

            <c>mss</c>
            <c>Microsoft Smooth Streaming</c>
            <c>RFCthis</c>
            <c><xref target="MSS">MSS</xref></c>

            <c>dash</c>
            <c>Dynamic Adaptive Streaming over HTTP (MPEG-DASH)</c>
            <c>RFCthis</c>
            <c><xref target="MPEG-DASH">MPEG-DASH</xref></c>
        </texttable>
       <t>[RFC Editor: Please replace RFCthis with the published RFC number for this document.]</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
         All security considerations listed in Section 8 of <xref target="RFC8007"/> and Section 7 of
         <xref target="RFC8008"/> apply to this document as well.
      </t>

      <t>This document defines the capability to use regular expression within the trigger spec for
         more granular content selection. The usage of regex introduced the risk of regex complexity attacks,
         a.k.a ReDos attacks. An attacker may be able to craft a regular expression that can exhaust server
         resources and may take exponential time in the worst case. An implementation MUST protect itself by
         at least accept triggers only from an authenticated party over a secured connection. An implementation
         SHOULD also protect itself by using secure programing techniques and decline trigger commands that use
         potentially risky regex, such techniques are readily available in secure programming literature and are
         beyond the scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors">
      <t>The authors would like to thank all members of the "Streaming Video Alliance" (SVA) Open Caching Working Group for
         their contribution in support of this document. </t>
    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">


      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3339" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8006" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8007" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8008" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8126" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8259" ?>

      <reference anchor="ABNF" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5234">
        <front>
          <title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker" role="editor">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="P. Overell">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2008" month="January"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>Internet technical specifications often need to define a formal syntax.  Over the years, a modified version of Backus-Naur Form (BNF), called Augmented BNF (ABNF), has been popular among many Internet specifications.  The current specification documents ABNF. It balances compactness and simplicity with reasonable representational power.  The differences between standard BNF and ABNF involve naming rules, repetition, alternatives, order-independence, and value ranges.  This specification also supplies additional rule definitions and encoding for a core lexical analyzer of the type common to several Internet specifications.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5234"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6707" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7736" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8216" ?>

      <reference anchor="PCRE841" target="http://www.pcre.org/">
        <front>
          <title>Perl Compatible Regular Expressions</title>
          <author surname="Hazel" initials="P"/>
          <date day="5" month="July" year="2017"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Version" value="8.41"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MPEG-DASH" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/65274.html">
        <front>
          <title>
              Information technology -- Dynamic adaptive streaming over HTTP (DASH) --
              Part 1: Media presentation description and segment format
          </title>
          <author>
             <organization>ISO</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="05" year="2014"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="23009-1:2014"/>
        <seriesInfo name="Edition" value="2"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MSS" target="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff469518.aspx">
        <front>
          <title>
              [MS-SSTR]: Smooth Streaming Protocol
          </title>
          <author>
             <organization>Microsoft</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="2017"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Protocol Revision" value="8.0"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ISO8601" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/40874.html">
        <front>
          <title>
              Data elements and interchange formats -- Information interchange --
              Representation of dates and times
          </title>
          <author>
             <organization>ISO</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="12" year="2004"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="8601:2004"/>
        <seriesInfo name="Edition" value="3"/>
      </reference>


    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
